A Guide to the Sayers Family Papers, 1779-1888
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Sayers Family Papers 1779-1888
Special Collections, Kegley Library
1993.3
9 folders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the estate of Samuel R. Sayers in 1993.
Biographical Information
William Sayers and his wife Esther Thompson Crockett Sayers settled in Wythe County in the mid-eighteenth century and raised three sons, Robert Sayers, Alexander Sayers, and John Thompson Sayers. The eldest son Robert Sayers (1754-1826) accumulated vast wealth during his lifetime including the profitable Anchor and Hope Plantation near Max Meadows. A bachelor, he willed the Anchor and Hope land to his nephew Robert Sayers.
John Thompson Sayers (1758-1816) served as a major in the Continental Army during the Revolutionary War and fought under Colonel William Preston. He was wounded severely at the battle of Cowpens, South Carolina on 17 January 1781. Surviving his wound, he married Susanna Crockett in 1784 and raised eight children including Robert Sayers I (1796-1876).
Their second son, Robert Sayers I inherited the Anchor and Hope Plantation. He and his wife, Senah Ross Sayers, raised eight children. Their sons, Robert Sayers Jr. (1826-1911), John Thompson Sayers II (b. 1831), and Samuel Rush Sayers (1833-1914) all served during the Civil War on the side of the Confederacy. Robert Sayers Jr. was a colonel of local militia while John Thompson Sayers II enlisted in 1861 in the Wythe Grays (Company 1, 4th Virginia Infantry Regiment) and eventually rose to captain. Federal troops captured him shortly after the battle of Gettysburg in July 1863 and imprisoned him at Johnson's Island near Sandusky, Ohio. Military records indicate that he was released in March 1865.
Dr. Samuel Rush Sayers was educated at the University of Pennsylvania during the mid-1850s and practiced medicine in Wythe County. During the Civil War he served as surgeon with the 4th Virginia Infantry Regiment and the 27 Virginia Infantry Regiment. For what he cited as personal reasons, Dr. Sayers unsuccessfully sought a resignation from the Army in May 1863. Citing his valuable medical knowledge and experience, military authorities refused his request and he continued to serve as surgeon throughout the war. Dr. Sayers married Lucy Ann Spiller; one his children was Robert Sayers III.
Scope and Content
The Sayers Family Papers are arranged in three series. Series I, Correspondence (1849-1888, Undated) includes letters received and sent to Senah Ross Sayers and her family from 1849 to 1888. Correspondents include Robert Sayers Jr., John Thompson Sayers II, Dr. Samuel Rush Sayers, Anne C. Sayers, and Robert Sayers III. Topics discussed in this correspondence document daily life at Anchor and Hope Plantation and Wytheville, Virginia. School life at Emory and Henry College (1849), Hampden-Sidney College (early spelling) (1888), United States Naval Academy (1888), and the University of Virginia (1888) is also covered in these letters.
The bulk of the correspondence, however, offers a fascinating glimpse at life during the Civil War from both a soldier's and civilian's perspective. Robert Sayers Jr. served as a colonel in the local militia while John Thompson Sayers and Dr. Samuel Rush Sayers both served in the Army of Northern Virginia, Confederate States Army. Samuel Rush Sayers worked as a regimental surgeon throughout the war with the 4th Virginia Infantry Regiment and the 27th Virginia Infantry Regiment. His letters reveal much of camp life and battles (Second Manassas, Winchester, Fredericksburg, Spotsylvania, Wilderness, and the siege of Petersburg). His brother served as a lieutenant and eventually captain of the Wythe Grays (Company A, Virginia Infantry Regiment). John Thompson Sayers was captured at Gettysburg and sent to Johnson's Island, a prison camp near Sandusky, Ohio. Several letters to and from the prisoner and family members are included.
Series II, Military Records (1779-1865) includes records of John Thompson Sayers including an order from Colonel William Preston in 1779 during the Revolutionary War and 1797 and 1799 commission papers as captain and major of the 35th Regiment, Virginia Militia.
Series III, Miscellaneous Records (1854-1863, Undated) contains records including a library card and lecture pass for Dr. Samuel Rush Sayers from the University of Pennsylvania Medical School in 1854. Also contained in this series is a Confederate States of America bond dated 1863 issued to Robert Sayers. Genealogical notes, newspaper clippings, and photocopies of correspondence in Series I complete this series. The photocopies contain a note in the upper left hand corner indicating in which folder the original will be found.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence. 1849-1888, Undated., 5 folders.
  - Folder 1. Correspondence. 1849, 1859., 2 items.
    - Letter. Robert Sayers Jr., Emory and Henry College, Emory, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Wytheville, Virginia. 15 October 1849., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:1)
    - Letter. Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to Ann C. Sayers, c/o Mrs. Susan Crockett Sayers Hoge, Giles County, Virginia. 21 February 1859., 3 p. (Folder-item 1:2)
  - Folder 2. Correspondence. 1861-1862., 9 items.
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Harpers Ferry, Virginia to Robert Sayers Jr., Wytheville, Virginia. 2 June 1861., 4 p. (Folder-item 2:1)
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Camp near Winchester, Virginia to Susan Crockett Sayers Hoge, Giles County, Virginia. 21 November 1861., 3 p. (Folder-item 2:2)
    - Letter. John Thompson Sayers, Camp near Winchester, Virginia to Dear Sister. 24 November 1861., 4 p. (Folder-item 2:3)
    - Letter. Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to Dear Daughter. 27 November 1861., 2 p. (Folder-item 2:4)
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Camp in Highland County, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia. 9 April 1862., 4 p. (Folder-item 2:5)
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia. 11 August 1862., 2 p. (Folder-item 2:6)
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Prince William County, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia. 31 August 1862., 4 p. (Folder-item 2:7)
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Richmond, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia. 10 December 1862., 2 p. (Folder-item 2:8)
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Yerby Hospital, Fredericksburg, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia. 14 December 1862., 1 p.; postscript, 2 p. (Folder-item 2:9)
  - Folder 3. Correspondence. 1863-March 1864., 5 items.
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Surgeon, 27th Virginia Infantry Regiment, Camp Paxton, Virginia to James A. Seddon, Secretary of War, Richmond, Virginia. 20 May 1863., 1 p.; fragment in 3 pieces. (Folder-item 3:1)
      Reverse has 1) note from Charles A. Haynes, Lieutenant Colonel Commanding, 27th Virginia Infantry Regiment, 20 May 1863; 2) note from Daniel M. Shriver, Lieutenant Colonel, 27th Virginia Infantry Regiment, 20 May 1863; 3) note from R. T. Coleman, Chief Surgeon, Johnson's Division, 21 May 1863; 4) note from Jubal A. Early, Major-General, 2nd Army Corps, 21 May 1863; 5) note from W. H. Taylor, Headquarters, Army of Northern Virginia, 21 May 1863; 6) note from L. Guild, Medical Director, Army of Northern Virginia; 7) note from W. H. Taylor, Headquarters, Army of Northern Virginia, 24 May 1863; note from C. A. Lee, Assistant Adjutant General, 30 May 1863. All concerning disapproval of Samuel Rush Sayers' request for resignation.
    - Letter. Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio. 13 October 1863., 1 p. (Folder-item 3:2)
    - Letter. Robert Sayers Jr., Wytheville, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio. 25 October 1863., 1 p. (Folder-item 3:3)
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Camp near Orange Courthouse, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Block No. 10, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio. 6 January 1864., 1 p. (Folder-item 3:4)
    - Letter. Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio. 7 March 1864., 1 p. (Folder-item 3:5)
  - Folder 4. Correspondence. April 1864-1865., 6 items.
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Camp Stonewall Brigade, [unknown] to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia. 6 March 1864., 2 p. (Folder-item 4:1)
    - Letter. John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Ohio to Sister. 9 April 1864., 1 p. (Folder-item 4:2)
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Field Hospital, [unknown] to Senah Ross Sayers. 6 May 1864., 2 p. (Folder-item 4:3)
      Location perhaps near Spotsylvania Courthouse, Virginia.
    - Letter. Anne C. Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio. 18 August 1864., 1 p. (Folder-item 4:4)
    - Letter. John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Ohio to Senah Ross Sayers and Robert Sayers Sr., Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia. 25 January 1865., 1 p. (Folder-item 4:5)
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Field Hospital, 2nd Corps, Army of Northern Virginia, near Petersburg, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia. 2 March 1865., 2 p. (Folder-item 4:6)
  - Folder 5. Correspondence. 1888, Undated., 5 items.
    - Letter. R. Crockett, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia to Robert Sayers III. 18 February 1888., 3 p. (Folder-item 5:1)
    - Letter. W. Mc [illegible], Hampden-Sidney College, Farmville, Virginia to Robert Sayers III. 21 June 1888., 7 p. (Folder-item 5:2)
      early spelling of Hampden-Sydney College.
    - Letter. Samuel Rush Sayers, Wytheville, Virginia to Robert Sayers III, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Maryland. 28 June 1888., 2 p. (Folder-item 5:3)
    - Letter. Robert Sayers III, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Maryland to Samuel Rush Sayers and Lucy Ann Spiller Sayers, Wytheville, Virginia. 3 October 1888., 2 p. (Folder-item 5:4)
      On reverse: [unknown] Sayers to Will [unknown].
    - Letter. Lucy Sayers, Wytheville, Virginia to Ellen B. Stuart, Saltville, Virginia. 8 January [unknown]., 2 p. (Folder-item 5:5)
- Series II. Military Records. 1779-1865., 2 folders.
  - Folder 1. Military Records. 1779-1799., 5 items.
    - Order from Colonel William Preston, Montgomery County, Virginia for Lieutenant John Thompson Sayers. 3 June 1779., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:1)
      Re: orders to impress provisions during march of Continental Soldiers to the northward.
    - Note from Jonathan Conger to Leader, Tory Expedition. 13 January 1790., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:2)
      Re: letter to Leader of the Tory expedition up New River to allow Lieutenant John Thompson Sayers to receive his pay.
    - Order from Colonel William Preston to Lieutenant John Thompson Sayers. 3 April 1780., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:3)
      Re: recruitment of men near the Lead Mines.
    - Appointment of John Thompson Sayers as Captain. 7 September 1797., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:4)
      Re: 35th regiment, 19th Brigade, 3rd Division of Virginia Militia.
    - Appointment of John Thompson Sayers as Major. 2 October 1799., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:5)
      Re: 35th Regiment, 19th Brigade, 3rd Division of Virginia Militia.
- Series III. Miscellaneous Records. 1854-1863, Undated., 2 folders.
  - Folder 1. Miscellaneous Records. 1854-1863, Undated., 4 items.
    Folder contains lecture pass dated 11 October 1854 and library card issued 18 October 1854 for Samuel Rush Sayers for use at the Pennsylvania Hospital. Lecture card was for lectures by Samuel Jackson, M. D., University of Pennsylvania. Also included is a Confederate States of America bond, issued to Robert Sayers, dated 1 September 1863 and undated genealogical notes on John Thompson Sayers and Susan Crockett Sayers.
  - Folder 2. Miscellaneous Records. 1849-1888, Undated., Photocopies.
    Photocopies of correspondence in Series I and newspaper clippings.